<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: conference | EngineerInk]]></title>
  <link href="http://technology.customink.com/blog/categories/conference/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://technology.customink.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-26T19:34:49-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://technology.customink.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[CustomInk]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Joy of Cooking - Whip Up a Rails Environment with Chef]]></title>
    <link href="http://technology.customink.com/blog/2012/05/25/the-joy-of-cooking-whip-up-a-rails-environment-with-chef/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-25T14:59:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://technology.customink.com/blog/2012/05/25/the-joy-of-cooking-whip-up-a-rails-environment-with-chef</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You've heard of Chef, Puppet, and other frameworks that can help you build out your infrastructure. You've been meaning to play around with one or more of them for some time now. Now's your chance; Start cooking up on your own servers!</p>

<p>In this presentation, I provide an introduction to Chef with a focus on what you'll need to know to get a Rails application up and running.</p>

<p>Topics include:
  * Introduction to Chef
  * Nodes, roles, environments, and other terminology
  * Introduction to cookbooks
  * Provisioning an environment for a Rails application
  * Deploying with Capistrano</p>

<p>You won't be ready to compete in Iron Chef, but you will be ready to serve up your own Rails environment in no time.</p>

<p>I gave slightly different versions of this presentation at <a href="http://www.rubynation.org/">RubyNation 2012</a> and <a href="http://chefconf.opscode.com">#ChefConf 2012</a>.</p>

<p>I'd really appreciate any comments, questions, or feedback in the comments section below.</p>

<h3>Video from ChefConf</h3>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/X1mmzERRkeI" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h3>Slides</h3>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="4fb421272cf6f5001f00ba85" data-ratio="1.2945638432364097" src="http://technology.customink.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taming the Kraken - How Operations enables developer productivity]]></title>
    <link href="http://technology.customink.com/blog/2012/05/25/taming-the-kraken-how-operations-enables-developer-productivity/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-25T14:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://technology.customink.com/blog/2012/05/25/taming-the-kraken-how-operations-enables-developer-productivity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At <a href="http://railsconf2012.com/">RailsConf 2012</a>, I gave a presentation on how our web operations team enables developer productivity.</p>

<p>There's always a bit of tension when getting features from idea to production. In this talk, I describe some of the changes CustomInk has made to reduce this friction and keep the new features coming. Gone are the days of bi-monthly deploys, office pools dedicated to guessing when this deploy will be rolled back, and the ceremony surrounding the deploy-rollback-fix-deploy cycle. Today, ideas flow from product managers to developers to production with ease thanks to a number of changes that we've made to our teams, processes and tools.</p>

<p>Presenting at RailsConf was a really enjoyable experience and the presentation was well received.  There were lots of questions from the audience after the presentation.  Unfortunately, the Q &amp; A section was not captured in the video.  I'd really appreciate any questions or feedback you have, just drop a comment below.</p>

<h3>Video</h3>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/5vzNzQzmAk0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h3>Slides</h3>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="4f96da12947c45001f018683" data-ratio="1.2945638432364097" src="http://technology.customink.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RubyNation 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://technology.customink.com/blog/2012/03/26/rubynation-2012/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-26T13:36:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://technology.customink.com/blog/2012/03/26/rubynation-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.rubynation.org/">RubyNation</a> is awesome.  Most ruby events are awesome, but in particular I enjoy RubyNation because it's local to me.  It's not that I don't like traveling to other conferences or that I think Washington DC is the best possible place for a conference.  What I love about RubyNation being local is having 200+ ruby developers from my immediate locale in one single place, at one single time.  Of course, it doesn't hurt to have <a href="http://onestepback.org">Jim Weirich</a> and <a href="http://coreyhaines.com/">Corey Haines</a> show up, either.</p>

<p>The other thing I love about RubyNation are all the great talks.  Even the bad talks are still good talks.  Even the terrible talks turn into great talks because when you step into the hallway, there are amazing people who showed up to RubyNation waiting to have a great talk with you.  Every year, without fail, I meet new people and learn new things.  I don't think you can put a price tag on that.</p>

<p>There were lots of highlights for me this year, and some surprises.  The first surprise should really have been no surprise at all, since it's a developing trend at all Ruby/Rails related events: JavaScript.  In his opening keynote, Justin Getland says something to the effect of "Adapt or die".  Justin's message was clear: wherever there is a gap, someone will be there to fill it.  There is a gap in JavaScript knowledge, so it's time to step in or someone else will.</p>

<p>The first day at RubyNation had one track that was entirely JavaScript and View focused.  The second track was a grab bag of ruby related topics such as toolkits or programming approaches.  Some of the JS/View track presentations that stuck out to me were:</p>

<p>Roy Tomeij's talk on <a href="http://roytomeij.com/slides/rubynation2012">Modular and Reusable Front-End code</a>,
Brennan Dunn's talk on <a href="http://speakerdeck.com/u/brennandunn/p/rails-without-views">Rails Without Views</a>,
John Athayde's talk on <a href="http://speakerdeck.com/u/boboroshi/p/the-rails-view-the-junk-drawer-grows-up">The Rails View: The Junk Drawer Grows Up</a>,
Chris Strom's talk on <a href="http://speakerdeck.com/u/chris/p/you-aint-spdy-ruby-nation">You Ain't SPDY</a></p>

<p>Andrew Glover's <a href="https://github.com/aglover/resque-example">Asynchronous Processing and Messaging</a> talk was a great introduction to Resque and Redis.  Although I didn't attend his talk, people told me that Mike Subelsky's talk <a href="http://www.subelsky.com/2012/03/slides-from-my-coding-for-uncertainty.html">Coding for Uncertainty</a> was amazing.  Before you knew it, Jim Weirich was wrapping up day one by teaching us how to use Ruby for purely functional programming purposes to implement the <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/karledurante/status/183312951598514176/photo/1">Y Combinator</a>.</p>

<p>Day two had a couple of front end related talks, but really seemed to focus more on some of the toolkits we use with ruby and some theory to help rubyists navigate the programming waters.</p>

<p>I really enjoyed Russ Olsen's <a href="http://speakerdeck.com/u/russolsen/p/eloquent-explanations-rubynation-2012">Eloquent Expressions</a> and Jeff Casimir's <a href="http://speakerdeck.com/u/j3/p/adventures-on-the-golden-path">Adventures on the Golden Path</a>.  As well, Patrick Peak and Nathen Harvey gave great talks on how to better organize your applications with <a href="http://speakerdeck.com/u/peakpg/p/plays-well-with-others-building-mountable-apps">mountable applications</a> and <a href="https://github.com/nathenharvey/cooking-with-chef">deployment strategies</a>, respectively.  <a href="https://github.com/ajburton">Anthony Burton</a> has posted a more <a href="https://gist.github.com/2182892">complete list of talks here</a>.</p>

<p>Corey Haines closed out the event with a call to arms for our community to mentor the next generation.  Corey's point was simple: there is a need for more developers.  Companies will step in to "make" new ones.  Do you want good developers or bad developers?  <a href="http://rubytutor.org/">Ruby Tutor</a> is a place where we can help to make the next generation great.</p>

<p>Thanks to all the people who made RubyNation such a great event this year.  See you all next year.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
