<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: kanban | EngineerInk]]></title>
  <link href="http://technology.customink.com/blog/categories/kanban/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://technology.customink.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-25T15:08:18-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://technology.customink.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[CustomInk]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taming the Kraken - How Operations enables developer productivity]]></title>
    <link href="http://technology.customink.com/blog/2012/05/25/taming-the-kraken-how-operations-enables-developer-productivity/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-25T14:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://technology.customink.com/blog/2012/05/25/taming-the-kraken-how-operations-enables-developer-productivity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At <a href="http://railsconf2012.com/">RailsConf 2012</a>, I gave a presentation on how our web operations team enables developer productivity.</p>

<p>There's always a bit of tension when getting features from idea to production. In this talk, I describe some of the changes CustomInk has made to reduce this friction and keep the new features coming. Gone are the days of bi-monthly deploys, office pools dedicated to guessing when this deploy will be rolled back, and the ceremony surrounding the deploy-rollback-fix-deploy cycle. Today, ideas flow from product managers to developers to production with ease thanks to a number of changes that we've made to our teams, processes and tools.</p>

<p>Presenting at RailsConf was a really enjoyable experience and the presentation was well received.  There were lots of questions from the audience after the presentation.  Unfortunately, the Q &amp; A section was not captured in the video.  I'd really appreciate any questions or feedback you have, just drop a comment below.</p>

<h3>Video</h3>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/5vzNzQzmAk0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h3>Slides</h3>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="4f96da12947c45001f018683" data-ratio="1.2945638432364097" src="http://technology.customink.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
